James O'Hara Cazenove Papers, 1898-1970
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
James O'Hara Cazenove Papers, 1898-1970
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
212
6 boxes (3.2 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Estate of James O'Hara Cazenove, 1984.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Cazenove family came to America from Geneva, Switzerland in the late 18th century and settled in Alexandria in 1797. The family, which was known for its shipping and importing business, married into the Lee family. James O. Cazenove (1880-1971), of 3756 Seminary Road, was the last of that name to live in Alexandria. His brother, Louis A. DeCazenove reverted to the use of "De" which had been dropped by the family when they came to this country. James and Louis were the sons of Louis A. Cazenove (1851-1925).
Scope and Content
The bulk of this collection deals with James O'Hara Cazenove's financial investments. Approximately half of the correspondence relates to legal/financial matters concerning the estate of J.O. Cazenove's father and brother, as well as his various mining investments. Some of the more interesting pieces are patents and designs for mixers and beaters, for which J.O. Cazenove was awarded patents between 1921 and 1923. His correspondents include William S. Barnes, Edmond W. Brown, Mary Lee Castleman, Carrie Stuart Davis, Jesse Larrabee, George Oldham, Edith Patton Cazenove, Ruth Y. Stuart, and Fred Stedman.
Among the items related to Louis A. DeCazenove are his thesis, Temperature Investigation in the Priestman Oil Engine, and a 1900 book called Songs of Cornell. DeCazenove's material also includes two scrapbooks: a 1898 to 1902 scrapbook about Cornell University, and a 1902 to 1925 scrapbook about Cornell University, the Dupont Company, cruises to Cuba and the West Indies, trips to Charleston, South Carolina, and other places, and the American Society of Mechanical Engineers.
Arrangement
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically and chronologically. Financial documents are by subject and chronological. Legal documents are chronological. Louis A. DeCazenove materials are by form.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Photographs transferred to photo collection.
Index Terms
American Society of Mechanical Engineers; Barnes, William S.; Brown, Edmond W.; Castleman, Mary Lee; Cazenove family; Cazenove, Edith Patton; Cazenove, James O'Hara, 1880-1971; Cazenove, Louis A., 1851-1925; Charleston, South Carolina--Description and travel; Cornell University; Cuba--Description and travel; Davis, Carrie Stuart; DeCazenove, Louis; Dupont Company; Eggbeaters; Larrabee, Jesse; Mixers (Cookery); Oldham, George; Stedman, Fred; Stuart, Ruth Y.
Contents List
- Correspondence, Miscellaneous A-C, 1902-1946 (Box-folder 212:1)
- Correspondence, William S. Barnes, 1922-1924 (Box-folder 212:2)
- Correspondence, Edmond W. Brown, 1935 (Box-folder 212:3)
- Correspondence, Edmond W. Brown, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 212:4)
- Correspondence, Edmond W. Brown, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 212:5)
- Correspondence, Mary Lee Castleman, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 212:6)
- Correspondence, Louis A. DeCazenove Jr., 1911-1931 (Box-folder 212:7)
- Correspondence, Louis A. DeCazenove, Jr., 1934-1951 (Box-folder 212:8)
- Correspondence, Carrie Stuart Davis, 1932-1949 (Box-folder 212:9)
- Correspondence, Miscellaneous F-M, 1903-1957 (Box-folder 212:10)
- Correspondence, Jesse Larrabee, 1922-1925 (Box-folder 212:11)
- Correspondence, Jesse Larrabee, 1926-1928 (Box-folder 212:12)
- Correspondence, Jesse Larrabee, 1929 (Box-folder 212:13)
- Correspondence, Jesse Larrabee, 1930 (Box-folder 212:14)
- Correspondence, Jesse Larrabee, 1931-1932 (Box-folder 212:15)
- Correspondence, Miscellaneous M, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 212:16)
- Correspondence, George Oldham, 1932 (Box-folder 212:17)
- Correspondence, George Oldham, 1934-1935 (Box-folder 212:18)
- Correspondence, Miscellaneous P-R, 1934-1959 (Box-folder 212A:1)
- Correspondence, Edith Patton [Cazenove], 1946-1968 (Box-folder 212A:2)
- Correspondence, Miscellaneous S-T, 1926-1968 (Box-folder 212A:3)
- Correspondence, Fred Stedman, 1937-1944 (Box-folder 212A:4)
- Correspondence, Fred Stedman, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 212A:5)
- Correspondence, Fred Stedman, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 212A:6)
- Correspondence, Fred Stedman, 1949-1953. n.d. (Box-folder 212A:7)
- Correspondence, Ruth Y. Stuart, 1936-1961 (Box-folder 212A:8)
- Correspondence, Ruth Y. Stuart, 1961, n.d. (Box-folder 212A:9)
- Correspondence, Miscellaneous U-Z, 1927-1968 (Box-folder 212A:10)
- Correspondence - Cards, 1927-1960 (Box-folder 212A:11)
- Financial Documents - Investments (Mines), 1924-1927 (Box-folder 212A:12)
- Financial Documents - Investments (Mines), 1928-1929 (Box-folder 212A:13)
- Financial Documents - Investments (Mines), 1930 (Box-folder 212A:14)
- Financial Documents - Investments (Mines), 1930 (Box-folder 212A:15)
- Financial Documents - Investments (Mines), 1931 (Box-folder 212A:16)
- Financial Documents - Investments (Mines), 1931(?) (Box-folder 212A:17)
- Financial Documents - Investments (Mines), 1932 (Box-folder 212A:18)
- Financial Documents - Investments (Mines), 1933-1936, 1956 (Box-folder 212A:19)
- Financial Documents - Investments (Stocks, CDs), 1913-1931 (Box-folder 212B:1)
- Financial Documents - Investments (Stocks, CDs, Real Estate), 1931-1954 (Box-folder 212B:2)
- Financial Documents - Estate of J.O. Cazenove (Commonwealth Trust Company) - Statement of Account, 1921-1925 (Box-folder 212B:3)
- Financial Documents - Estate of J.O. Cazenove (Commonwealth Trust Company) - Statement of Account, 1926-1929 (Box-folder 212B:4)
- Financial Documents - Estate of J.O. Cazenove (Commonwealth Trust Company) - Statement of Account, 1930 (Box-folder 212B:5)
- Financial Documents - Estate of J.O. Cazenove (Commonwealth Trust Company) - Statement of Account, 1931-1932 (Box-folder 212B:6)
- Financial Documents - Estate of J.O. Cazenove (Commonwealth Trust Company) - Statement of Account, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 212B:7)
- Financial Documents - Estate of Louis A. Cazenove (American Security and Trust Company), 1925-1929 (Box-folder 212B:8)
- Financial Documents - Estate of J.O. Cazenove (American Security and Trust Company), 1931-1955 (Box-folder 212B:9)
- Financial Documents - Statements, 1940-1969 (Box-folder 212B:10)
- Financial Documents - Receipts, 1946-1969 (Box-folder 212B:11)
- Financial Documents - Retainers from M. Ferguson, 1956-1961 (Box-folder 212B:12)
- Legal Documents - Patents, 1921-1932 (Box-folder 212B:13)
- Legal Documents - Insurance, 1935 (Box-folder 212B:14)
- Legal Documents - Insurance, 1942(?)-1961 (Box-folder 212B:15)
- Legal Documents - Litigation, 1925-1932 (Box-folder 212B:16)
- Printed Material, 1921-1961 (Box-folder 212B:17)
- Printed Material - Clippings, 1913-1917 (Box-folder 212B:18)
- Miscellaneous - Medical Records, 1932 (Box-folder 212B:19)
- Miscellaneous - School Records, 1903-1951 (Box-folder 212B:20)
- Miscellaneous (Lists, notes, ephemera, image The Waterfall) (Box-folder 212B:21)
- Louis A. DeCazenove, 1902-1934 (Box-folder 212B:22)
- Louis A. DeCazenove - Cornell Scrapbook, 1898-1902 (Box 212C)
- Louis A. DeCazenove - Scrapbook, sheet music (She Was Bred in Old Kentucky, diplomas, 1910-1925 (Box 212D)
- Louis A. DeCazenove - Thesis, Temperature Investigation on the Priestman Oil Engine and Songs of Cornell, 1903; 1900 (Box 212E)